<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Media_Server_User_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<chapter id="ittms-Introduction_to_the_Media_Server">
	<title>Introduction to the &THIS.PLATFORM; Media Server</title>
	<para>
	The &THIS.PLATFORM; Media Server is an open source, software based 
	implementation of the VoIP network element responsible for media handling. It 
	supports IP and TDM interfaces, and can act as both a Media Server and as a 
	Media Gateway. It provides support for both distributed and centralized 
	services, including circuit switch voice/video, announcements and tones.
	</para>
	<para>
	In the modern VoIP world, providers offer highly customized services that 
	combine media such as audio, video and IM. These services require dedicated 
	and customized media processing capabilities. To achieve this, the VoIP 
	network separates the media processing functions into a dedicated node which 
	is responsible for media processing only, while all the intelligence is 
	executed by the separate call controller. The node processing the media 
	streams is called a Media Server.
	</para>
	<para>
	The media handling node must also be able to bridge the gap between 
	traditional legacy systems and modern VoIP networks. This node is typically 
	called a Media Gateway.
	</para>
	<para>
	The &THIS.PLATFORM; Media Server can operate with the &THIS.PLATFORM; JAIN 
	SLEE Application Server. However, the Media Server comes with a telco 
	standard MGCP interface, which allows you to use another call controller if 
	desired.
	</para>
	<para>
	The &THIS.PLATFORM; Media Server is also equipped with an implementation of 
	the media control API compliant to JSR-309 specifications, which allows you 
	to use the Media Server with the &THIS.PLATFORM; SIP Servlet Container.
	</para>
	<para>
	The Media Server includes an embedded signaling gateway	function which 
	supports the complete set of TDM and IP signaling protocols. It supports TDM 
	access variants like ETSI ISUP, PRI, as well as supporting signaling backhaul 
	over IP with M3UA and SUA options.
	</para>
	<para>
	The Media Server is implemented using the JBoss Microcontainer kernel, which 
	allows you to archive maximum flexibility. It gives you the ability to adopt 
	the Media Server for task specific actions, and/or extend the functions of the 
	Media	Server by installing additional media processing components.
	</para>
</chapter>
